[Music]
my video on kombucha is one of the first
I ever did even featured in my blog
nutritionfacts.org the first month where
I marveled at the fact that i' reached
nearly a 100,000 people and now I'm
honored to say we reach more than
100,000 a day but that first kombucha
video I profiled a report published in
the Journal of intensive care Medicine
of a case of Kombucha toxicity young guy
ending up an acidotic coma which
concluded that while kombucha is
considered a healthy Elixir The Limited
evidence currently available raises
considerable concern that it may pose
serious health risks consumption of this
tea should be discouraged it may be
associated with a life-threatening
lactic acidosis this was just one of
several case reports of serious and
sometimes fatal liver dysfunction in
lactic acidosis within close proximity
of ingestion for example two cases in
Iowa of severe metabolic acidosis
including one death the triggering of a
life-threatening autoimmune muscle
disease requiring emergency surgery
probably related to kombucha shaking
shortness of breath in a movement
disorder after consumption of tea and no
other medications xerostomia dizziness
nausea vomiting headache and neck pain
which recurred on reingestion of the tea
the another case of severe metabolic
lactic acidosis is a case of
hepatotoxicity liver toxicity that
result after stopping
cucha why these sporadic cases maybe
some unusual toxins developed in a
particular batch I mean it is a
fermented product so it's possible and
just some are contaminated by some bad
bug like the time people smeared
kombucha on their skin because they were
told it had magical healing power
what instead it had was Anthrax growing
in it so even though such reports were
rare 10 years ago I concluded maybe we
should stick to foods that haven't put
people in a coma but look everything in
life is all about risks versus benefits
maybe it's worth it after all it's
reputed to cure cancer eliminate
wrinkles and even restore gray hair to
its original color marketed by
alternative and naturopathic healers
throughout the United
States currently kombucha is praised as
the ultimate health drink or damned as
unsafe claimed to be a universal
wonderful drug known as a purifying
potion but is it a potion or poison
evidently back in the 20s 30s and 40s
there were several medical studies
conducted by recognized Physicians
confirming all sorts of beneficial
effects I couldn't wait to read them
okay so they site uh do new friend in
farmworth okay there it is same claim
citing Allan okay what's Allen
1998 oh you gotta be kidding me right
you're citing some Rando kombucha
website and here it is defunct since
2001 sourced citation list from stuff
that was posted on some mailing
list finally in 2003 a systematic review
of the clinical evidence that was
published and the main result of the
systematic review was the total lack of
efficacy data no clinical studies were
found so we just have these you know
these cautionary tail case reports and
so on the basis of these data it was
concluded that the largely undetermined
benefits do not outweigh the documented
risks of Kombucha can therefore not be
recommended okay but that was back in
2003 how about a 2019 systematic review
of the empirical evidence of human
health benefit
the nonhuman subjects literature claim
numerous health benefits of Kombucha
meaning mice and rats but what we need
are human clinical trials and still not
a single controlled human study but they
did find one uncontrolled study showing
a significant before and after reduction
and fasting and after a meal blood
sugars among type two diabetics
nonetheless despite no controlled trials
a significant commercial shelf space is
now dedicated to kombucha products and
this's this widespread belief that the
products promote health so we're left
with this kind of extreme disparity
between science and belief with little
convincing clinical evidence yet Health
claims that are as far-reaching as they
are implausible while the potential for
harm seems
considerable in such extreme cases
healthc Care Professionals should
discourage consumers from using and
paying for anything
that only seems to benefit those who
sell it
[Music]